Music is the most universal language that we have,
الموسيقى هي أكثر اللغات التي نمتلكها عالميةً،
way more so than any dialect or tongue.
فهي أكثر من مجرد لغة أو لهجة محكية.
You can play a melody to a child in China
يمكنك أن تعزف لحنًا لطفل من الصين
and the same melody to a child in South Africa.
ونفس اللحن لطفل آخر من جنوب أفريقيا.
And despite the huge differences between those two children,
وعلى الرغم من الاختلافات الكبيرة بين هذين الطفلين
they will still draw some of the same truths from that melody.
سيلامس اللحن كليهما بنفس الطريقة.
Now, I think the reason why music has this universality,
الآن، أعتقد أن السبب الذي جعل الموسيقى تحظى بهذه العالمية،
this way of speaking to each and every one of us,
هي الطريقة التي تلامس فيها كل شخص فينا،
is that somehow it's capable of holding up a mirror to us
وكأن لها بطريقة ما قدرة على حمل مرآة لنا.
that reveals, in some small or large way,
والتي تظهر لنا، بطريقة أو بأخرى
a little bit of who or what we are.
قليلًا من هويتنا وحقيقتنا.
By logical extension of this,
بالتعبير المنطقي عن هذا،
if music is this universal force,
إذا كانت الموسيقى تشكل هذه القوة العالمية
then surely groups of musicians -- let's call them orchestras --
فبالتأكيد مجموعة الموسيقيين، أو لنطلق عليهم فرق الأوركسترا،
should reflect every aspect of the community.
يجب أن يعكسوا كل جانب من المجتمع.
Logical, but not necessarily true.
كلام منطقي، ولكن ليس من الضرورة أن يكون واقعيًا.
At TEDxBrussels today, we've been looking forward to the future --
في TEDxBrussels اليوم، نقوم بالبحث عن المستقبل
50 years from now.
50 عامًا من الآن.
Well, I'm going to ask you to go in the other direction for a minute,
أود أن أطلب منكم الذهاب إلى الاتجاه الآخر لدقيقة،
the early 1960s to be precise.
لأوائل الستينيات على وجه التحديد.
And if you took a look at all the great orchestras
إذا ألقيتم نظرة على جميع فرق الأوركسترا العظيمة
of the world at that time, a snapshot,
في العالم في ذلك الوقت، بنظرة خاطفة،
how many women do you think you would find
كم امرأة تتوقع أن تجد بينهم
playing in those orchestras?
يعزفن في هذه الفرق؟
The answer: virtually none.
الجواب: لا أحد تقريبًا.
Well, here we are 50 years on, in 2011,
نحن هنا بعد 50 عام، في عام 2011،
and pretty much every orchestra on the planet
أنا متأكد أن كل أوركسترا على الكرة الأرضية
has a fantastic and healthy balance between the sexes.
يوجد بها توازن رائع بين الجنسين.
"Of course!" I hear you say, "Totally logical."
أسمعكم تقولون "بالتأكيد.. كلامه منطقي تمامًا".
But how about another aspect of the community?
ولكن ماذا عن الجانب الآخر من المجتمع؟
The disabled community.
مجتمع ذوي الاحتياجات الخاصة.
Do we find them well-represented in the great orchestras of our world?
هل نجدهم بشكل ملحوظ في أي أوركسترا حول العالم.
Well, I can tell you as a conductor,
بإمكاني أن أقول لكم كقائد لأوركسترا،
I work with orchestras around the world all the time,
أعمل مع الأوركسترا في جميع أنحاء العالم في كل وقت،
and I can count on the fingers of one hand
ويمكنني أن أعد على أصابع يد واحدة
the number of disabled musicians I've encountered
عدد الموسيقيين ذوي الاحتياجات الخاصة الذين التقيتهم
in any orchestra,
في أي أوركسترا
anywhere.
في أي مكان.
Why is this?
لماذا هذا؟
You can't tell me that there aren't millions upon millions
لا يمكنك إخباري أنه لا يوجد الملايين
of prodigiously gifted musicians of disability around the world.
من الموسيقيين الموهوبين من ذوي الاحتياجات الخاصة حول العالم.
Where is their platform?
أين منصتهم؟
Where is the infrastructure that creates a space for them
أين البنية التحتية التي تخلق مساحة لهم
so that they can collaborate with other great musicians?
حتى يتمكنوا من التعاون مع موسيقيين رائعين آخرين؟
So, ladies and gentlemen, as you can probably tell,
لذا، سيداتي وسادتي، كما يمكنكم أن تعرفوا،
And this mission has a personal root to it.
وهذه المهمة تربطني بها علاقة شخصية.
I have four children, the youngest of whom was born with cerebral palsy.
لدي أربعة أبناء، أصغرهم ولدت مصابة بشلل دماغي.
She's now five, and through her glorious existence,
عمرها الآن خمس سنوات، وأثناء وجودها الحافل
I suppose I have now become a fully paid-up member
أفترض أنني أصبحت الآن عضوًا مسددًا لكامل اشتراكاته
of the amazing, dizzyingly wonderful disabled community.
لمجتمع ذوي الاحتياجات الخاصة الرائع.
And I find myself looking at the Paralympics
ووجدت نفسي أبحث في البارالمبية (ألعاب أولومبية للمعاقين)
and thinking what an incredible model that is.
وأعجبت بعظمة هذا النموذج.
It's taken a good five decades, actually,
استغرق الأمر خمسة قرون جيدة، في الواقع،
but I can say with hand on heart
لكن بإمكاني أن أقول بكل صدق
that when the Paralympics comes to London next year,
أنه عندما تأتي البارالمبية إلى لندن في العام المقبل،
there will not be an intelligent person anywhere on the planet
لن يكون هنالك أي شخص ذكي في أي مكان على هذا الكوكب
who does not absolutely believe in the validity of disabled sportspeople.
لا يؤمن بصحة رجال الرياضة ذوي الاحتياجات الخاصة.
What an amazing position to be in!
يا له من مكان عظيم لنكون فيه!
So, ladies and gentlemen, where the hell is music in all this?
لذا، سيداتي وسادتي، أين الموسيقى من كل هذا؟
Apologies to any of you who are sports fans,
اعتذاري لأي شخص منكم من مشجعي الرياضة،
but music is far more universal than sport.
لكن الموسيقى أكثر عالمية من الرياضة.
Where is the platform? Where is their voice?
أين منصتهم؟ وأين أصواتهم؟
So, we in the UK are at the very early stages in forming what will be
نحن في المملكة المتحدة في المراحل الأولى من تشكيل ما سيكون
Britain's first-ever national disabled orchestra.
أول أوركسترا وطنية بريطانية لذوي الاحتياجات الخاصة.
We are going to call it the British Paraorchestra,
وسنطلق عليها باركيسترا البريطانية،
because with the world's eyes on London next year
لأننا سنلفت نظر العالم في العام المقبل
and particularly on the Paralympics,
ولا سيما في الألعاب الأوليمبية،
we want to throw down the gauntlet
نريد أن نثبت أنفسنا
to every single other country that is represented there,
لكل بلد آخر موجود هناك،
to say to them, "Here's our paraorchestra.
لنقول لهم، "هؤلاء فرقتنا الباركيسترا.
Where's yours?"
أين فرقتكم؟"
Every country should have a multiplicity of paraorchestras
وينبغي أن يكون لكل بلد فرقة باركيسترا متعددة ومتنوعة
of all shapes and sizes,
بكل الأشكال والأحجام،
no question.
لا شك في ذلك.
Now, today is a very special day for me,
اليوم يعتبر يومًا مميزًا بالنسبة لي
because it is the first time that the first four members
لأنه ولأول مرة أول أربعة أعضاء
of my little embryonic paraorchestra
لفرقتي الصغيرة
are going to play in public;
سيعزفون علنًا؛
four extraordinary musicians of which the number will grow and grow.
أربعة موسيقيين غير عاديين وسيكبر عددهم أكثر وأكثر.
I hope in the end the Paraorchestra could even be as big as 50 musicians.
وأتمنى أن يصل عدد أفراد الفرقة إلى 50 شخص.
We present to you today a little sonic adventure,
سنقدم لكم اليوم مغامرة صوتية صغيرة،
a little piece of improvisational whimsy, if you like,
قطعة صغيرة من الارتجال غير الجاهز، إذا أردت،
a piece on which, of course, the ink is still wet,
قطعة فنية لا تزال ألوانها رطبة،
the clay is still wet.
الطين لا يزال رطبًا.
After all, improvisation is never a fixed thing.
في النهاية، الارتجال لا يكون دائمًا ثابتًا.
We decided what we wanted to share with you,
قررنا أن الشيء الذي نود مشاركته معكم،
at the heart of our improvisation,
من قلب ارتجالنا،
was a tune which is beloved of British people.
هو لحن محبب للشعب البريطاني.
It's one of the only folk melodies
وهو واحد من الألحان الشعبية
that we still recognize in our culture.
التي لا نزال نميزها من ثقافتنا.
And here's an interesting thing: folk music can tell you an awful lot
وهنالك شيء مثير حول الموسيقى الشعبية حيث أنها تبين لك
about the cultural DNA of the country from which it originates.
العديد من الأمور الفظيعة حول الأصل الثقافي للبلاد التي تنشأ منها.
You see, we in Britain are quietly melancholic.
ترى، نحن في بريطانيا حزينون قليلًا.
You know, the rain ... it does rain.
تعلمون بأنها تمطر هنا.
The food's not so good.
الطعام ليس جيدًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Quietly melancholic.
كئيب بعض الشيء.
Not blackly so, just quietly so.
ليس سوداويًا بشكل كبير، بشكل قليل فقط.
And as Shakespeare put it so brilliantly in "Twelfth Night,"
أو كما عبر عنها شكسبير بذكاء في مسرحيته "الليلة الثانية عشرة"،
he loves music that has "a dying fall."
كان يحب الموسيقى التي يوجد فيها إيقاع مميت.
So this melody, "Greensleeves," is chock-full of "dying fall."
لذلك اللحن "غرينزليفس" لحن شعبي بريطاني مليء بالإيقاعات المميتة.
You may know this tune.
من الممكن أن تعرف هذا اللحن.
(Singing) Da, da, da da da da, dying fall.
يغني..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Brief burst of sunshine, ladies and gentlemen, the chorus --
يوجد بصيص من الأمل، سيداتي وسادتي..
(Singing) Ya da da da, dying fall ...
يغني..
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
OK?
حسنًا؟
It's like we need some melodic Viagra in our culture, ladies and gentlemen.
وكأننا نحتاج إلى بعض حبوب الفياجرا في ثقافتنا، سيداتي سادتي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It goes without saying
من البديهي القول
that we are very much at the starting gates with this project.
أننا على بوابات البداية لهذا المشروع.
We need your help, we need the global community
نحتاج إلى مساعدتكم، كما نحتاج من المجتمع العالمي مساعدتنا
to help us deliver this dream,
على تحقيق هذا الحلم،
so that this orchestra can be full steam ahead
لتتمكن هذه الأوركسترا من بدء العمل بالمشروع بهمة
by summer 2012.
بحلول صيف 2012.
If you think there's any way that you can help us,
إذا كنت تعتقد أن بإمكانك مساعدتنا بأي طريقة،
please, please, get in touch.
أرجوك.. أرجوك أن تفعل.
And so, ladies and gentlemen, it gives me enormous pride, pleasure and joy
سيداتي وسادتي، بكل فخر وفرح وسرور يسرني
to introduce to you, with a short improvisation
أن أقدم لكم هذا الارتجال القصير
upon that most melancholic tune, "Greensleeves,"
لأكثر الألحان كآبة "جرينسليفز"،
the first four members of the British Paraorchestra.
أول أربعة أعضاء من فرقة باركيسترا البريطانية.
(Applause) (Cheers)
(تصفيق) (تحية)
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
(Cheers) (Applause)
(تحية) (تصفيق)